Hi, I'm the glute guy, Brett Conturus,
and I just wanted to film a quick video
to show you guys how I conduct my EMG
research. EMG stands for
electromyiography. And the first step is
to get uh electrodes and place them on
your body parallel with the the muscle
fibers of the muscle you're trying to
record. So I normally don't wear
spandex. In fact, this is the only time
anyone will ever see me in spandex. But
this electrode is on my vasis lateralis.
This one here is on my my adductors.
This one my biceps porous. And then I
have a hole cut out from the spandex to
measure my glutius maximus. And then
here's the
ground. So that's the first step is
placing the the electrodes where you
want them. Uh the next step is
attaching the electrodes to the myotrace
itself. Okay. Now as you can see I have
all the electrodes and wires hooked up
and taped onto my leg with some slack.
So the electrodes go get pulled glutes
uh biceps for vasis laterals adductors
and the myotrace 400 is turned on. Now
the next step is getting the software
system set up. So all I do is I click on
the software system. Now I choose which
muscles I want to record. So the first
pair of electrodes I have hooked up to
my glute max. The next pair I have
hooked up to my vasis
lateralis. The next pair to my
adductors. And the next pair to my
biceps for. So now this software knows
which muscles are uh being recorded and
then I'm going to choose over here the
processing. So
um I'm going to choose
uh
rectification
smoothing and amplitude
normalization. Now I don't have to do
anything to the data once I record it.
It knows how to do it. Now this signal
right here from the myotrace is picked
up via
Bluetooth. So the Bluetooth records the
signals and then uh all I have to do is
choose the the interval for the data
that I want. Um so now the the next step
is to record MVC which is right here.
MVC stands for maximum voluntary
contraction. That that's what we're
going to do
next. Okay. Now we need to record MVC
for each muscle group. Now, I'm just
going to show you one of those
positions, but each muscle group has its
own position you need to get in to test
your maximum voluntary contraction. For
the glutes, it happens to be the
quadripan hip extension position. So,
I'm going to get in that position. I
squeeze my glute as hard as I can
possibly squeeze. I'm flexing my butt as
hard as I can. The software is picking
that up. So, it's going to use that MVC
to rank every exercise that I do to that
maximum voluntary
contraction. Okay. So, here's what it
looks like when I record MVC. I click on
MVC. It picks up the
connection. I squeeze my glutes as hard
as I can, which you can see right
there. I hit
record. It's recording that. That's as
hard as I can squeeze them. And I hit
finish. Now it asks me to store it. So,
as you can see, there's the maximum
voluntary contraction for the glutes.
And now I'm going to hit start, and I
can start recording different exercises.
So, okay. So, now we're going to test a
few different exercises. The first one
I'm going to do is the full squat. Now,
I have 275 lbs on the bar. That's around
my eight rep max. So, I'm going to keep
this uh this uh study consistent and use
my eight rep max for every exercise. So,
here's the squat. Now, this is sending
signals which is being picked up by
Bluetooth to the software program. So,
here's the squat.
Okay, so this is the report it gives me
for the 275 lb full squat. This here
shows the glute activity mean and peak.
Mean would be the average activation
throughout the exercise and peak would
be the highest uh point of tension that
it reached. Here's the vasis
lateralis
adductors and biceps forous. Now, uh
I'll give the numbers at the end of this
video, the exact
numbers. Okay. Now, I have 185 lbs on
the bar and I'm going to do a Bulgarian
squat or as Mike Bole likes to call it,
a rear foot elevated split squat. So,
again, this is around 80 rep max.
Okay. And this is the report that we get
for the 185 lb Bulgarian squat. Here's
the glute activity, mean and peak, uh,
vasis lateralis, adductors, and biceps
for. And I'll go over these numbers at
the end of the
video. All right. Now, we're going to
test the deadlift. I have a 405 on the
bar. It's around my A rep max. So, let's
let's test the deadlift right
now. Okay. So, here's the report for the
405 lb deadlift. Glutes, quads,
adductors, biceps,
forest. All right. Now, we're going to
test the single leg RDL. I have 90 lb
duckos. So, 180 lb
total. So, this is the report for the 90
lb single leg RDL. Glute mean and peak,
vasis lateralis mean and peak, adductors
mean and peak, and biceps for mean and
peak. I'll have the exact numbers at the
end of this
video. Okay, now we're going to test the
hip thrust. I have 405 lbs. It's about
my favorite
max. Okay, this is the report for the
405 lb hip lift.
glutes, vasis lateralis, adductors,
biceps
for Okay, now we're going to test the
band uh scorcher hip thrust.
Okay, this is the report for the blue
band scorcher hip thrust glute mean and
peak vasis lateralis adductors and
biceps
foras. Now let's analyze the results.
The full squat gives us the most mean
and peak quadriceps activity. The
conventional deadlift gives us the most
mean and peak adductor activity as well
as the most peak hamstring activity.
The 405 lb hip thrust gives us the most
mean hamstring activity and the band
scorcher hip thrust gives us the most
mean and peak glute activity and ties
for the most mean quadriceps activity.
Now when you analyze the biomechanics of
these different lifts, it makes sense
when comparing it to the EMG results.
The reason why the band scorcher hip
thrust works so well for the glutes is
your shoulders and feet are elevated up
onto a a platform and the bands come
from down low. So you have to squeeze
your glutes as hard as possible to push
your hips forward against that
resistance. And when you do the
exercise, you literally feel your glutes
almost ripping off the bone. But unless
you have a scorcher, there's really no
way to replicate that exercise. So, the
next best thing for the glutes would be
to use the 405 pound hip thrust with
your shoulder shoulders elevated onto a
bench. Uh, I hope you enjoyed the video.
I hope this sheds some light on EMG
research and I hope it inspires more
people to utilize uh EMG research. Um,
as strength coaches and trainers, we
always rely on the researchers, but
there's no reason why we can't be doing
research ourselves. As you can see from
this video, it's really, really easy.
So, you can get one of these
Myotrace 400s from Noraxin and their
website is nuraxin.com.